בוקר טוב. Boker tov. דף Daf is נ"ו, Nun-vav, fifty-six, and we
continue into the discussion of יין נסך yayin nesech and at what
stage does it become יין? yayin? And I think this lovely here
sort of picture that I drew, I think the one mistake I
made, which I think I was sensing as I was drawing it,
was that this place where they're stomping, that's like the גת gat
itself. There's not like another place where they pile of the stuff.
Okay, so that line in the משנה mishna that you're like lifting
it up and moving it to the תפוח, tapuach, I think just
means that like you're lifting it and you're re-trying to like pull
put the stuff to the middle, you know what I mean? But
it doesn't mean that you're bringing it to another place. There was
that line in the משנה mishna that distracted me, because the משנה
mishna speaks about, you know, you have the stuff in the גת,
gat, you lift it up, you bring it to the תפוח tapuach
and then it goes into the בור. bor. But again, I think
the תפוח tapuach is just the reshifting of it, even if you're
lifting, reshifting it. Anyway, there are basically two places: the גת, gat,
the funnel or whatever, not the funnel, whatever it is, the pipe
or whatever it is, down into the ground, and then you got
the בור. bor. Anyway, so the question is
when does it become יין? yayin? So that there's a problem of
getting הנאה hana'ah from it and relatedly so that there's a problem
of being paid to work with it because the Rabbis don't want
you to be paid to work with איסורי הנאה. issurei hana'ah. So
the משנה mishna says that at this stage it's not יין, yayin,
presumably even at this stage it's not יין. yayin. It's only יין
yayin when it hits the בור. bor.
And that's when it becomes forbidden. I mentioned before and I'll touch
on it again (ha ha, touch on it), that there's a question,
does it become יין yayin here now it's forbidden because the non-Jew's
energy caused it to move? So once it hits there it's even
without touching it, like there's an idea of כוחו, kocho, which we'll
get to, even without direct touch. Or does it mean that if
it's touched at that stage, it becomes forbidden? But anyway, that's the
משנה, mishna, that it only becomes יין yayin at that stage.
The גמרא gemara presented the position of רב הונא Rav Huna that
says that as soon as it starts traveling, it becomes forbidden even
before it hits the בור. bor. The language is כיון שהתחיל להימשך,
keivan she'hitchil lehimashech, okay? And the גמרא gemara basically tried to reconcile
it with the משנה, mishna, but in the end said that it
was a later position, משנה ראשונה, mishna rishona, משנה אחרונה, mishna achrona,
that actually disagreed with the משנה, mishna, but the authors of the
משנה mishna apparently there's a revision of this idea and then it
quoted this idea that originally they said בדד, b'dad, then they said
בדבה b'dabbah or whatever, דבה, dabbah, okay? So anyway, and then the
interesting debate of in תוספות Tosafos is when is that stage of
התחיל להימשך? hitchil lehimashech? Is it only when it sort of leaves
the barrel? Or even if it is in here's the case, in
the barrel and it sort of collects at the bottom, would that
already be a problem? And that led to תוספות Tosafos's whole discussion
of can they if they have a small barrel where the stuff
doesn't leave, but like maybe sometimes it does collect at the bottom,
okay, would that be a problem of doing that together with a
non-Jew? Or does it actually have to leave the barrel, which is
more I think the פשט pshat of the גמרא, gemara, but anyway,
I mean who knows? להימשך lehimashech sounds like it's going out. But
anyway, that's an interesting question there. But certainly if it's all mixed
together and it hasn't pooled, it's not yet יין, yayin, okay? So
that was the basic discussion point of the גמרא. gemara. Then there
was a whole other issue going on, which I'm not going to
review, which is very important about
about what do you call it, about מסייע לידי עוברי עבירה. mesayei'a
lidey ovrei aveira. The non-Jew isn't doing an עבירה, aveira, because he's
not prohibited about getting things טמא. tamei. But of course for a
Jew he would be doing an עבירה, aveira, and even if the
עבירה aveira is already done, if the action is continuing, you're not
allowed to participate with him in the action. So therefore you can't
be stomping together here with a Jew, if the Jew is doing
it בטומאה, b'tumah, and there was an interesting, I said I wasn't
going to review it and now I'm reviewing, and then there was
an interesting debate of רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos whether מסייע mesayei'a
includes the process leading up to it as well. Does sort of
gathering the grapes or whatever is the leading up process as well?
But anyway, certainly the after, you know once the עבירה aveira is
done, it's done. And that becomes very relevant in other areas of
הלכה, halacha, what are the parameters of מסייע לידי עוברי עבירה? mesayei'a
lidey ovrei aveira? Okay, back to the גמרא gemara now. נ"ו עמוד
א', nun-vav amud aleph, okay? ואינו עושה יין נסך עד שירד לבור.
ve'eino oseh yayin nesech ad she'yered l'bor. So now this once again
we're revisiting yet again the question about at what stage does this
סתם stam become defined as יין? yayin? So our משנה mishna says
when it gets to the בור. bor. We revised it with רב
הונא Rav Huna to say when it starts to come out. But
now we're going to see that in a context of מעשר, ma'aser,
it's going to be later stages even than
that. Okay, והתנן, vehatnan, one minute we taught in a משנה: mishna:
יין משיקפה. yayin misheyekpeh. Wine is considered that the מלאכה melacha is
done to it, the processing is done and it's חייב chayav in
תרומות ומעשרות, trumos u'ma'asros, from the time that it floats. Now what
does it mean it floats? So רש"י Rashi says it means that
like the lees of the wine float on top of the grapes
float on top of the wine. Apparently that's a later stage in
the בור. bor. First it starts collecting, but eventually, I mean you
know, I guess a little bit of the lees come out and
eventually... eventually there's some like layer of those like grape skins or
whatever that are floating at the top, okay? So that happens I
don't know at some later stage during the process of it going
into the בור. bor. It's not immediate. It's not like a different
thing you do, it's just I guess as the wine continues to
collect. Okay, so it's not immediately when it goes into the בור.
bor. So אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so how do you reconcile that?
Presumably, if that's when we consider it to be wine for תרומות
ומעשרות, trumos umasros, shouldn't it be the same for the הלכות halachos
of יין נסך? yayin nesech? So אמר רבא לא קשיא, Amar Rava
lo kashya, הא רבי עקיבא הא רבנן. ha Rabbi Akiva ha rabbanan.
It's a debate, it's a debate by תרומות ומעשרות trumos umasros and
it's the same debate here by יין נסך. yayin nesech. דתנן, Detnan,
actually this is דתניא, detanya, it's pretty funny. The first one, we
have התניא hatanya and דתנן, detnan, and it's actually the reverse, דתנן
detnan והתניא. vehatanya. We taught in the ברייתא, braisa, דתניא, detanya, יין
משיורד לבור. Yayin misheyered labor. When is wine considered wine for תרומות
ומעשרות? trumos umasros? When it hits the well, the you know the
בור, bor, not the well, whatever, the cistern. רבי עקיבא אומר משיקפה.
Rabbi Akiva omer misheyikpeh. No, only when the only when the lees
begin to like float. Okay, so our משנה mishna that says משיורד
לבור misheyered labor is the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. The משנה mishna
in מעשרות Maasros that says that it's only this state of משיקפה
misheyikpeh where the skins float on the top, a later stage, that's
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. All right, fine, it's a debate of תנאים.
Tannaim. איבעיא להו, Ibaiya lehu, now they ask the question. קיפוי דבור
או קיפוי דחבית? Kipui debor o kipui dechavis? Is it the floating
on top of on top of in the in the in the
cistern, okay, or is it after you take the stuff out of
the cistern? Because remember here you were bringing, you know, all of
your barrels so that after the wine gathers, you put them in
your barrels and then you're going to, I don't know, bring them
to market or something. So then after you put it in here,
it'll float on top of the barrel. So that's obviously a much
later stage. Okay, or later stage. So which one? קיפוי דבור או
קיפוי דחבית? Kipui debor o kipui dechavis? תא שמע, Ta shema, come
and hear, דתניא, detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braisa, this one
is actually, no, this is דתנן, detnan, every דתניא detanya is דתנן,
detnan, everyone is reversed. יין משיקפה, Yayin misheyikpeh, אף על פי שקפה,
af al pi shekappah, now it goes from the time it begins
the stuff begins to float on top of it. אף על פי
שקפה, Af al pi shekappah, now even once the stuff is floated
on top of it, קולט מן הגת העליונה ומן הצינור ושותה. koleis
min hagass haelyona umin hatzinor veshoseh. You can still get some wine
from here. This is not a סתם יינם stam yeinam issue, no
non-Jews in the picture. This is a case of תרומות ומעשרות. trumos
umasros. You can still take from here or take from the צינור,
tzinor, from the pipe, you know, and take some wine there and
eat it and without taking תרומות ומעשרות. trumos umasros. Even though the
stuff is floating over here and the stuff down here is חייב
chayav in תרומות ומעשרות, trumos umasros, we're not גוזר gozer and tell
you that you can't eat the rest. You can take wine from
here or here and it's still okay to eat it without taking
תרומות ומעשרות. trumos umasros. That's the teaching of the משנה. mishna. This
is not a very straight צינור tzinor
here. Anyway, so what does that tell you? So שמע מינה קיפוי
דבור קאמרן. Shema mina kipui debor ka-amran. שמע מינה, Shema mina, since
we're contrasting the floating here, although it's floating here and that's a
problem, you can still take it from here and here, obviously we're
talking about the floating here. If we were talking about even if
it's floating in the barrels, you can still take it from here,
that'd be like obvious, it's not even part of the whole setup.
Okay, so since we're contrasting floating with this, obviously we mean the
floating that's going in the cistern. Okay, so שמע מינה, shema mina,
that's a good proof. Okay, so now we've got the idea that
according to this, in by cases of תרומות ומעשרות, trumos umasros, there's
actually a debate whether it means the well or whether it means
the floating in the well, the floating in the בור. bor. I
keep on saying well, whatever, cistern. And our משנה mishna that says
it's the cistern itself, the earlier stage, is the position of the
חכמים. Chachamim. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva would say a later stage. Okay,
but now we got a problem. הגמרא Hagemara says like this, one
minute, והתני רזבי דבי רבי אושעיא, Vehatni Razvi devei Rabbi Oshaya, but
רזבי Razvi taught, teaches in the name of רבי אושעיא. Rabbi Oshaya.
יין משי, Yayin mishe,
he has a different ברייתא. braisa. And here's how his ברייתא braisa
teaches it.
Everybody is bumped one stage. Everybody is one stage further. יין משיורד
לבור ויקפה. Yayin misheyered labor veyikpeh.
The first position is not the cistern, but it's the cistern plus
the the grape leaves are now floating on top. Not leaves, whatever,
the grape skins are floating on top. That's before now we thought
that was רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. This now is the תנא קמא.
Tanna Kamma. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is an even later stage than
that. This is all about תרומות ומעשרות. trumos umasros. אומר משישלה בחביות.
Omer misheyishleh bachaviyos. Okay, so
so it's only once you take it out of the cistern and
you, you know, you sort of scoop it out with the barrels.
So everybody is one stage further. So now nobody says the position
of just the בור bor itself, which is the position of our
משנה. mishna. All right? So everybody now is one stage further. So
the גמרא Gemara says תרצה נמי להך קמייתא הכי. Tirtza nami lehach
kamaisa hachi.
Okay fine, we can reconcile this ברייתא braisa with the earlier ברייתא
braisa with the I mean with the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva and the רבנן. rabbanan. I mean we can reconcile it by
editing the earlier ברייתא braisa to say the same thing. Okay, we'll
read the earlier ברייתא braisa to say the following: משיורד לבור ויקפה.
misheyered labor veyikpeh.
That the ברייתא braisa that said משיורד לבור misheyered labor doesn't just
mean
it goes into the
cistern. אומר משישלה
בחביות. Omer misheshleh bachaviyot. Alright, fine, whatever. So we can edit the
ברייתות Braitot that they're all saying the same in a later stage.
But we still got a problem, right? Because our problem is that
we have our משנה Mishnah that says משיורד לבור. misheyared labor. Alright,
so now all the רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and the רבנן Rabbanan
are all one or two stages later than that. So what are
you going to do with our משנה? Mishnah? So the גמרא Gemara
says ואלא מתניתין דקתני אין עושה יין נסך עד שיורד לבור Ve'ela
matnitin dektani ein oseh yain nesech ad sheyared labor which is an
earlier stage than those two, לימא תלתא תנאי היא? layma telata tannai
hi? Should we say there's a three-way debate of תנאים, Tannaim, which
sort of makes sense since we had to edit an earlier משנה
Mishnah by תרומות ומעשרות Trumot u'Maasrot also? So it seems like there
are three stages that are being debated. So the גמרא Gemara says
should we say that there's a third position out there and we'd
say by תרומות ומעשרות Trumot u'Maasrot also just as soon as it
hits the well? No, so the גמרא Gemara says שאני יין נסך
דאחמירו ביה רבנן. Shani yain nesech de'achmiru bei rabbanan.
No,
maybe we could say that by תרומות ומעשרות Trumot u'Maasrot everybody agrees
it's one of these later stages, the floating of the skins or
the going into the barrels. But by יין נסך Yain Nesech we
decided to make it an earlier stage even as soon as it
hits the well even if nobody would say that right by even
if nobody would say that by תרומות ומעשרות. Trumot u'Maasrot.
So this is סתם יינא Stam Yeina really, right? We don't know
this יין נסך, Yain Nesech, right? Yeah.
So is this saying סתם יינא, Stam Yeina, רבנן, rabbanan,
תרומות ומעשרות Trumot u'Maasrot are דאורייתא? de'Oraisa?
Well first תרומות ומעשרות Trumot u'Maasrot are probably not דאורייתא de'Oraisa בזמן
הזה, bizman hazeh, but that's a good point, but you know even
so it's associated with עבודה זרה avoda zara so it would be
it certainly is conceivable that we're more מחמיר machmir by this דרבנן
derabbanan than we would be by that דאורייתא, de'Oraisa, but that's a
good point. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so it says where were we? So לרבא, le'Rava, so look
at this we're almost over before we begin today. ולרבא דלא שני
ליה, U'leRava de'lo shani leh, so now רבא Rava who did not
give who דלא שני ליה, de'lo shani leh, right רבא Rava when
he basically originally asked the question right about this case of מעשר
Maaser and he tried to say okay our משנה Mishnah is the
חכמים Chachamim it's not רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, רבא Rava could have
given an answer like oh no no no by מעשר Maaser we're
just more you know lenient, by עבודה זרה avoda zara we're more
strict. So since רבא Rava could have made that distinction and he
didn't he tried to reconcile everything so clearly רבא Rava wants תרומות
ומעשרות Trumot u'Maasrot to be the same as עבודה זרה, avoda zara,
okay, and not say that עבודה זרה avoda zara is stricter. So
if that's true what do you do with the fact that by
תרומות ומעשרות Trumot u'Maasrot we see the opinion משיקפה misheyikfeh and the
barrels and by עבודה זרה avoda zara we just see the opinion
of משיורד לבור. misheyared labor. So rather than saying עבודה זרה avoda
zara is stricter if you think that they would all be the
same position which seems to be רבא's Rava approach you would have
to say that there really are three positions by תרומות ומעשרות, Trumot
u'Maasrot, which by the way it sounds like since we went through
a whole lot of editing the sense is that there are these
three positions by תרומות ומעשרות Trumot u'Maasrot as well. So the גמרא
Gemara says ולרבא דלא שני ליה, u'leRava de'lo shani leh, רבא Rava
who doesn't give that answer that distinction okay between סתם יינא Stam
Yeina and doesn't make a distinction between סתם יינא Stam Yeina and
תרומות ומעשרות Trumot u'Maasrot and he would say they're all the same
debate. So מוקים לה כתלתא תנאי, mokim lah ketlata tannai, yes he'd
say there's three debates of תנאים, Tannaim, one is at יין, yain,
floating, barrels or the earlier stage of בור. bor. And by the
way תוספות Tosafot points out it's really you know if you go
by the משנה אחרונה Mishnah Acharona there's we in the end wind
up saying an earlier stage than that, we say even משיחול להמשך.
misheyachol lehimashech. So that could be according to רבא Rava maybe that
early teaching would say the same by תרומות ומעשרות, Trumot u'Maasrot, okay,
but or whatever you could say is the even you know at
this stage it's saying whatever תרומות ומעשרות Trumot u'Maasrot story is it's
like at the בור, bor, the floating, the later, by יין נסך
Yain Nesech we're making it this earlier stage, by סתם יינא Stam
Yeina we're being stricter. But רבא Rava might say whatever you say
by one you're saying by the other it's the same issue you
know between תרומות ומעשרות Trumot u'Maasrot and יין נסך. Yain Nesech. Alright?
Okay, so that was a lot. We're already halfway done with the
דף. daf. What are you going to do with the rest of
our time today? Anybody have any good movies you want to see?
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, we'll do a
little of the תוספות Tosafot but it is going to go pretty
quickly in terms of the גמרא Gemara you know we it's a
short גמרא Gemara because תוספות Tosafot is discussing the practical implication. Okay.
מה שבבור אסור והשאר מותר. Ma shebabor asur vehashear mutar. So this
is forbidden this is permissible that's again assuming the משנה ראשונה Mishnah
Rishona that it's only once it hits the בור. bor. So אמר
רב הונא לא שנו אלא שלא החזיר גרגוסני
לגת. Amar Rav Huna lo shanu ela shelo hechzir gargusni legat. That's
only if you haven't returned the the basket to the גת. gat.
אבל החזיר גרגוסני לגת אסור. Aval hechzir gargusni legat asur. So so
if you return the basket to the גת gat to the press
to the stomping space then it's forbidden. What's the basket? So at
the end of this funnel here and if I can call it
a funnel this whatever
this
trainer?
No the גרגוסני gargusni is the basket the basket is a strainer
I know, okay. This is I mean I'm just looking for the
word for that that's a pipe, thank you. I don't know why
I can't come up with the word pipe. Okay. You had something
that looked sort of like a basket like this. Okay? And it's
a, like think of like a woven basket, it's a strainer, it's
a sieve. Okay, so the wine goes through here, it goes into
this basket, and it comes out like this. Why is it doing
that?
Well, you want to get it like a little bit out of
the skins and the seeds and whatever.
You want to get the skins and the wine out. Right, so
it's to strain the wine.
Now obviously not entirely because then it flows back up in there.
Right, exactly. So some of it comes out, but it does its
first job of straining the wine. So if you went ahead and
you took this thing and you went back and put it in
here, I don't know why you'd put it in there, I'm not
sure what you're using it for or whatever, there's got to be
something.
Maybe to have it strained at the very beginning.
Maybe, maybe they keep on moving it for maybe I don't know.
Maybe there's extra juice still in
there and they want to get yeah but then you can get
the juice out down there, why do you want to bring it
back there?
But for whatever reason maybe it needs to be crushed
more to get more juice out.
Oh, oh, that's a good point! You get the lees and you
want to oh you bring the skins, oh that makes sense. Excellent.
Okay, so you bring the skins and you dump it back there.
So what he's saying is then you're going to have a little
of this liquid that's going to still that's going to be in
here. Okay? And you're right, you're probably bringing the the the skins
back to press more, but a little bit the drops of juice
are going to be there, it's going to go back in here,
that liquid is going to mix up, this liquid is already forbidden,
it's going to mix up and it's going to make what's back
there forbidden as well.
Now there's a lot that's a very interesting there's a lot of
implications about that. The question the גמרא's Gemara going to say is
wait, why is the liquid in here forbidden? It didn't go into
the בור Bor yet.
But he
says משיחלה להמשך. misheyichaleh lehimashech.
No, no, no, this is all still within the משנה ראשונה Mishna
Rishona that it's only when it gets to the בור. Bor. So
we're going to have to explain why the little bit of liquid
is forbidden there. We'll get back to that in a minute. But
let's also talk about why why it makes the rest of this
forbidden. Okay, you have a few drops of what one first of
all the other thing that should be pointed out is that the
simple sense here is that nobody has touched this yet. It's just
it's flowing you take it, it's already סתם יינם. stam yeinam. That
gets to an important debate that תוספות Tosafot has. Once it gets
in the well, is it forbidden because only after it's touched by
a non-Jew or is it forbidden because a non-Jew did the stomping
and his energy brought it into there? So the simple sense of
this is that it's just forbidden automatically. But let's just acknowledge that
and move on. So now the question is you bring this back
here and a few drops goes in there. Okay, why is that
make it forbidden? It's a few drops obviously there's a lot more
here than a few drops of wine. What's the story? Okay, so
this raises a question about what is the שיעור shiur for סתם
יינם stam yeinam to be בטל. batel. All right. From this it
makes it sound like it's even a כל שהוא, kol shehu, even
a tiny amount. But the problem is even when we say a
tiny amount a כל שהוא, kol shehu, we normally say that if
it's like a case of מין במינו min bemino where it's mixed
up in the like thing. So if it was mixed up in
other if this was other grape juice and it was grape juice
and grape juice forbidden and permissible we could say a tiny amount
makes it forbidden. Okay. But there's a lot most of this is
grapes, not grape juice over here, okay, and that's like a מין
בשאינו מינו, min beshe'eino mino, they're two different types of things, so
why doesn't the grapes nullify the few drops of wine? That's the
question תוספות Tosafot asks. Who cares that they're a few drops of
wine or of grape juice? So תוספות Tosafot says well one minute
is are grapes and grape juice מינו mino or אינו מינו? eino
mino? The same thing or different things? On the one hand they
pretty much taste the same, like it's just one is just a
squished version of the other. On the other hand they're called different
things, grapes and unfermented wine. So this we're going to see is
a debate of אביי Abaye and רבא Rava later on. Whether to
determine מינו mino and אינו מינו eino mino if we're saying that
even a tiny amount makes the same thing forbidden, do you go
by שמא shma or טעמא? tama? What it's called or how it
tastes? If you go by what it tastes like, then we can
answer this. It assumes מין במינו min bemino is is not בטל
batel even in a כל שהוא kol shehu and it assumes all
of this is considered מינו mino because it all tastes the same.
It all tastes like this grape juice that was just squeezed. But
if you go by שמא shma what it's called, then grapes are
different than grape juice. So we still don't understand why this is
not בטל. batel. Okay, that's the question that תוספות Tosafot asks. All
right. And תוספות's Tosafot so let's take a quick look at this
תוספות Tosafot since we have a little extra time. All right. אלא
אם החזיר גרגוסני לגת אסור ela im hechzir gargusni legat assur תוספות
Tosafot says פירוש peirush אף מה שבגת af mah shebagat מפני שטיפות
יין שבגרגוסני mipnei shetipot yayin shebagargusni מתערב בגת. mitarev bagat. The drops
of wine mix up. ואם תאמר והלא מיסתמא יש בגת יותר משישים
מטיפות היין שבגרגוסני. ve'im tomar vehalo mistama yesh bagat yoter mishishim mitipot
hayayin shebagargusni. What do you mean? There's got to be 60 times
more. ורמינהו לקמן חמר חדתא בענבי רבא אמר בנותן טעם uremi'inhu lekaman
chamar chadta be'invei rava amar benoten ta'am that when you have fresh
wine and grapes רבא Rava calls that an אינו מינו eino mino
and he says it's בטל batel if it's less than one sixtieth
if it doesn't taste right וקיימא לן כרבא לגבי אביי vekaima lan
kerava legabi abaye and we rule
like רבא Rava so it should be בטל. batel. וכי תימא כיון
דבגת נמי איכא יין עם ענבים vechi teima keivan debagat nami ika
yayin im anavim one minute, but in addition to the grapes there's
also other grape juice in this גת gat והוי ליה מין במינו
דבמשהו ולא
בטיל vahavei lei min bemino debemashehu velo batil but... minute, he says,
it's okay, but there's also a little grape juice, and maybe it's
not בטל batel the grape juice. So then תוספות Tosafos says, I
won't go into it, he says the basic principle is, but if
the grapes are enough to be מבטל mivatel it, the presence of
the grape juice shouldn't prevent it from being בטל. batel. So we
still got a problem; why aren't the grapes מבטל mivatel the few
drops of wine? So he says ויש לומר, v'yesh lomar, I'm skipping
under the parenthesis, דסבירא ליה כאביי דאמר חמרא חדתא בענבי במשהו ולאית
ליה נמי סלק את מינו כמי שאינו. d'svira leh k'Abaye d'amar chamra
chadeta b'invay b'mashehu v'lais leh nami salik es mino k'mi she'eino.
So his first answer is, yeah, maybe this גמרא Gemara assumes not
like רבא, Rava, assumes like אביי, Abaye, assumes it's all considered to
be מינו, mino, it's all considered to be like it's the same
thing, and therefore a few drops makes it forbidden. Okay, and then
he goes on with another answer, da da da da da. Okay,
and finally he says that maybe at the last line of תוספות,
Tosafos, right above the word גרגוסני, gargusni, he says ויש לומר דרב
הונא כרב רבה סבירא ליה דוקא כאידנא דסבירא כרבי יהודה מין במינו
במשהו בכל איסור שבתורה. v'yesh lomar d'Rav Huna k'Rav Rabba svira leh
davka k'idnash d'svira k'Rabbi Yehuda min b'mino b'mashehu b'chol issur shebaTorah.
This isn't just a הלכה halacha about סתם יינם; stam yeinam; maybe
he's of the opinion we always say יין נסך yayin nesech is
במשהו. b'mashehu.
Okay, it still doesn't explain the question of the אינו מינו aino
mino of the grapes. All right, so one question תוספות Tosafos has
is it sounds like a few drops makes this forbidden. That would
make sense if we said that we go by במשהו b'mashehu and
if we considered everything to be מינו, mino, but both of those
are questionable assumptions, certainly the idea that we consider everything to be
במשהו. b'mashehu. There's a very important debate in the ראשונים: Rishonim: how
do we rule by סתם יינם? stam yeinam? Not by יין נסך
yayin nesech itself. How do we rule by סתם יינם? stam yeinam?
Do we rule by סתם יינם? stam yeinam? Okay, if you look
at the second wide line of that תוספות, Tosafos, because that's also
the ואם תאמר, v'im tomar, he says לפירוש רבינו תם דמפרש לקמן
בפרק בתרא, l'peresh Rabbeinu Tam d'mifarash l'kamman b'perek Basra,
that's not פרק ב׳, perek beis, פרק בתרא, perek Basra, דסתם יינס
בשישים כשאר איסורין. d'stam yeines b'shishim k'shaar issurin.
Okay,
so there's two questions here, right? One is, we know that יין
נסך, yayin nesech, okay, יין נסך yayin nesech is במינו במשהו. b'mino
b'mashehu. But
here there's two questions, okay, that's, that's the principle. Question number one
is, is סתם יינם stam yeinam בשישים b'shishim or במשהו? b'mashehu?
That's question number one. And question number two is that it's only
במינו b'mino that we say it, right? So here we've got a
problem. Here, first of all, it's סתם יינם, stam yeinam, so according
to רבינו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, it should never be במשהו. b'mashehu. And
number two is, even if it is במשהו, b'mashehu, it should be
considered אינו מינו, aino mino, okay, because the grapes and the wine
are different things, they're not the same thing. So anyway, תוספות Tosafos
raises all those issues; he tries to figure it out, what position
this גמרא Gemara is taking, but it might not be—the point is
the הלכה. halacha. להלכה, l'halacha, we might say this is considered אינו
מינו, aino mino, and we might also say that סתם יינם, stam
yeinam, as opposed to יין נסך, yayin nesech, is sixty and not
במשהו. b'mashehu. All right, so that's point number one: a few drops
of grapes makes it forbid—a few drops of the grape juice makes
it forbidden.
תוספות Tosafos says why.
Now the גמרא—see Gemara that, and again, like all that, like, stuff
that you were saying, I think at the very beginning, like, when
you, if you buy something with a little bit of, you know,
grape stuff, like you do today, it's, it's all בטל batel anyway,
because it's most of סתם יינם. stam yeinam.
Exactly, exactly. So now the question is, okay, why is the stuff
here, back to this, why is this a problem? Whether it's been
touched by a גוי goy or it's just the גוי's goy energy
moved it, it hasn't yet gone into the בור. bor. And this
is משנה ראשונה, Mishna Rishona, that it has to go into the
בור. bor. So that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to focus on.
Let's look at the גמרא. Gemara.
So the גמרא Gemara says
גרגוסני כפופה במה קמיסרי? gargusni kfufa b'mai kamissari? How does the גרגוסני
gargusni become forbidden? It didn't go into the בור bor yet. בניצוק,
b'nitzok, because of pouring. Meaning, this is the idea of ניצוק חיבור.
nitzok chibbur. Since what's in the בור bor is forbidden—again, presumably forbidden
even without touch,
automatically—and it's connected to the stuff that's in this, in this sieve,
in this basket, through, through like a stream, so it's like it's
all one unit. And if that's forbidden, the stuff in the basket
is forbidden as well, okay.
And you can't take that back a step and say, well, if
the stuff in the basket—excellent question.
That's what this תוספות Tosafos is about. We'll get to that in
a minute, okay. The גמרא Gemara says, שמע מינה ניצוק חיבור? shma
mina nitzok chibbur? Should we infer from there that ניצוק nitzok is
חיבור? chibbur? Because it means—and maybe we don't want to conclude that
way, because we're going to see that it's a debate later on.
So we often don't like to be forced into a particular position,
okay. So,
so should we therefore infer from this ruling that, that pouring is
considered a connection? גמרא Gemara says, not necessarily, כדתני רבי חייא שפחסה
צלוחיתו. k'd'tani Rabbi Chiya shepachasta sluchitoso. As רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya will
explain later, it's a case where basically it's sort of slapping against—remember
פחסה pachasta was when you sort of flatten the idol—so the liquid
here is slapping against the, the pitcher. הכי נמי שפחסה בורו. hachi
nami shepachasto boro. The, the well is like slapping against the barrel—which,
the, the basket—which basically means as: forget ניצוק חיבור. nitzok chibbur. The
reason this is an issue, this is an issue, is in a
case where the well is full. And if the well is full—I
keep on saying well, whatever, the cistern is full. So therefore stuff
that's already in the cistern is now coming in contact with the
bottom of the basket. So it's not stuff that has yet to
go into the cistern, that stuff is not a problem. It's stuff
that's gone into the cistern and now because the water level is
so high, the wine level has doubled back into the bottom of
the basket and that now is being carried back. Okay, so that's
all very nice, but now we're going to deal with the implications
of the נצוק. nitzok. Okay, yes, what did you want to say?
I thought you said the flow itself causes everything.
The גמרא Gemara says that's one way of reading it, but then
the גמרא Gemara says that would force us to conclude that flow
is a connection and we don't want to necessarily conclude that, we
want to leave that as an open question. So if you want
to leave that as an open question, the way to explain it
is not because of the flow but because of the wine level
itself hits the basket. Okay, so now the question is according to
that approach that the flow is a connection, okay, why did you
not say it all the way back to here? Right? Why is
it only this is a problem and all of this is okay?
All of this is part of the same flow. And if you'd
say we're no longer dealing with the wine level, so it's all
part of the same flow. Why not say that this is forbidden
as well? So based on this, רש"י Rashi rules that a נצוק
בר נצוק, nitzok bar nitzok, a flow that derives from a flow
is not connected. Now what makes this a flow that derives from
the flow? Like if I've got my filter on my you know
on my sink or whatever, I don't even know what I'm drawing
here, but anyway, okay if I've got my filter on my sink
and like this, okay I don't call that the flow of the
flow of a flow, okay if I'm touching this it's all one
continuous flow, right? So what makes this a flow of a flow
רש"י Rashi says is that it basically changes directions, okay at least
the way תוספות Tosafot explains it is that it's sort of like
I don't know it's something like this that it like like the
sieve is like maybe at this stage like maybe it's at the
sides, okay and maybe it's like the wine hits here, collects here
and then switch and then goes out on the side. So something
like that it's considered to be not the original flow but somehow
a second-degree flow. Okay, it doesn't go straight, it hits and it
moves and then it comes out again. All right, so anyway and
therefore it's like an angle there somehow?
What? So that's so it's coming out from the side.
Yeah, so you would have to change this picture. Okay, so if
it is a flow of a flow it's not a problem and
this therefore leads to the following scenario okay which is תוספות Tosafot
describes the following case. If you take a look it's always interesting
when he practically applies it. This huge תוספות, Tosafot, okay sometimes the
big ones are easy. He says ומעשה בא u'maaseh ba yes if
you go one two three four five six
seven where was it eight ומעשה
בא?
u'maaseh ba?
Yeah where's it eight lines down bottom of ויש אומרים. v'yesh amrim.
No
no no that's another מעשה. maaseh.
I just lost it I had ומעשה בא u'maaseh ba a second
ago. Okay yeah it's one two one two three four five six
seven about eight lines eight lines from the wide lines three words
before the end of the line ומעשה בא. u'maaseh ba. People see
that? Yeah Gloria you got that?
Four lines into the big תוספות. Tosafot.
Yeah okay eight lines from the where the lines get wide. You
have it Gloria? ומעשה בא לפני u'maaseh ba lifnei last word on
the line is
לפני. lifnei. Okay where it says רש"י Rashi six lines down two
lines after that is לפני. lifnei. Okay ומעשה בא לפני רש"י בעובד
כוכבים ששפך יין מן הקנקן לכוס ואז נאסר היין שבכוס משום דמדי
נפיק לבראי גזרו ביה רבנן כדיתא לקמן פרק ב והיין שבקנקן נאסר
נמי מטעם נצוק. u'maaseh ba lifnei Rashi ba'oved kochavim sheshofach yayin min
hakan-kam lekos v'az ne'esar hayayin shebakos mishum d'maidei nafek l'barai gazru bei
rabbanan k'de'itah l'kammon perek bet v'hayayin shebakan-kam ne'esar nami mitaam nitzok. Okay
so stage number one is okay you took your nice wine bottle
let's see if I can draw a wine bottle probably not
something like this right? Okay anyway you took your nice wine bottle
okay and here's your cup of wine and poured the wine into
it. Now and here's the un-Jew. Now the question is this was
all כשר kosher wine okay so first of all the question is
does that wine become forbidden? He didn't touch that wine that's again
a case of כוחו kocho okay right? This is a classic case.
You have a non-Jewish person serving יין מבושל yayin mevushal wine. The
assumption is that you can't drink if he does that you can't
drink the wine in the cup and you can't drink the wine
left in the bottle. Why is that? He never touched the wine.
So number one is that you assume that because of his כוח
koach his energy pulled made that wine come out that's like he
touched that wine. That's why the wine in the cup is forbidden
okay because of כוחו. kocho. Then that goes back and makes the
wine in the bottle forbidden because of נצוק nitzok right? Because
it's connected through to the flow. Okay, so now the wine in
the bottle is forbidden. That was stage number one or two. Okay,
that's ניצוק. nitzok. מטעם ניצוק ועכשיו משך ישראל יין מן החבית לקנקן
והתירה רש"י. mitam nitzok ve'achshav mashach yisrael yayin min hachavit lekankan vehitira
rashi. Okay,
and then what you did was, you went at stage number three
and you have your big barrel of wine here and you've got
whatever, okay, your little thing, your thing, and you took that same
קנקן kankan because you weren't thinking or whatever, okay,
okay, and you now have your barrel of wine and you had
a little of this wine left from over there and you filled
that up again with wine. That was stage number three. So the
question is, wait, this wine that's here now forbidden because it was
ניצוק nitzok should now make all the wine in the barrel forbidden
because of the other ניצוק nitzok of this new flow. Do people
get that? But those are different ניצוק. nitzok. This is all one
thing over here. I understand, I understand. So it's even more removed
than this.
So is it a change of direction though that we were talking
about?
Well here also, this is forbidden and it makes the stuff at
the top of the pouring.
Yeah but that's one flow, but I'm saying the diagram over here,
is this a change of direction that might be related to this
קנקן? kankan?
Well yeah, that's the point. Not a change of direction, but it's
a second stage. So now this, should it make what's back up
here forbidden? And רש"י Rashi said no, that's a second degree ניצוק.
nitzok. I mean if we say this is a second degree ניצוק
nitzok where it's one process, we're certainly going to say this is
a second degree ניצוק. nitzok. So רש"י Rashi said the stuff there
is okay.
But does that bottle wine still because it's אסור? asur?
That bottle wine remains forbidden.
Yeah, even though you added like,
yeah, that would go with ביטול bitul but it probably wouldn't be
enough to do ביטול. bitul. So that's רש"י's Rashi principle that ניצוק,
nitzok, a second degree ניצוק nitzok is okay and that's how he
explains this case. But I'm now going to tell you a very
different way to explain this case. Yes?
I was thinking, just to follow up, I think a little acronym
for this would be that ניצוק, nitzok, the classic case of ניצוק
בר ניצוק nitzok bar nitzok is that. Because it's literally two degrees.
Yeah, and the angle, the idea of the angle, comes to turn
case where it's presumably a direct flow, but into a קנקן. kankan.
So it's like a ניצוק בר ניצוק. nitzok bar nitzok. That's why
the angle is secondary to the actual.
Yeah, this to call this a two degree remove is a big
חידוש. chiddush. But if that you're going to be okay with, you're
certainly going to be okay with this. Now, comes along, that was
רש"י's Rashi approach. But comes along, whoever it was who disagreed with
רש"י, Rashi,
I forget, we'll have to find it here, but someone here disagrees
with רש"י Rashi and he says, I can't find who, and now
the sun is in my eyes. Anyway, the opposing position says: No,
I don't understand your question to begin with. This question makes no
sense. Your question was, what a stupid question, Michael, just using you
as a participant. You said, oh, why don't we say because of
ניצוק nitzok that all of this will be forbidden? Okay, and you
came up with this answer of ניצוק בר ניצוק. nitzok bar nitzok.
He says: No, the stuff in here isn't considered wine yet. Even
if you touched it directly it wouldn't be forbidden. So of course
it doesn't make this stuff forbidden. If it's like this, right, where
it's already wine, it's come out of the well or whatever, yeah,
maybe you even do two degrees removed. I don't know, maybe. Okay,
the reason, and maybe this is all one flow anyway, you're not
maybe you're not entitled to call this two flows. It doesn't matter,
it doesn't make it forbidden
because this stuff isn't wine yet. And that's why it's not forbidden.
Okay, it has nothing to do with the fact that it's two
degrees removed. Of course the question that you should be asking me
is: When you put it back? Then this also isn't wine yet.
So why is the גמרא Gemara saying that ניצוק nitzok makes it
forbidden? So according to this approach, this approach says no, actually once
it's in the basket, it already is like it's in the בור.
bor. It already is wine. Okay, so when the גמרא Gemara says
משיורד לבור, misha yarad labor,
according to this read, this is already משיורד לבור. misha yarad labor.
No, when you put it back in there though, that's wine, but
that stuff over there isn't. Then it's totally not
מינו.
meino. That doesn't... well, okay, that's an interesting question about defining מינו
meino if it's the juice but not yet halachically wine. But I
don't want to get into that right now. I want to finish
this explanation. Because this explanation says let this all be ניצוק. nitzok.
You can't make this forbidden because this isn't wine. Okay, but then
how does this become forbidden? Okay, so this would actually say that
once it's in the basket it's in the category of משיורד לבור.
misha yarad labor. Of course then the question should be, then why
do you need the principle of ניצוק? nitzok? Once it's in the
basket it's a problem. So this would say, ah, because it doesn't
become a problem automatically because the non-Jew stomped on it. It's only
a problem once a non-Jew touched it. So the way he reads
this is that this is now the case, this is now the
בור, bor, once it's in the basket, and a non-Jew came and
touched that wine. So you got
it? All of this is halachically wine, okay, but it's not forbidden
yet. The non-Jew touched this, and then it also makes the stuff
in... the basket forbidden because of ניצוק, nitzok, but it's because all
of it is considered wine. It can't make this forbidden because that
isn't wine. Okay? So two very different ways of reading this משנה.
mishna. You gotta appreciate the point that's being made here. Like how
could ניצוק nitzok make a difference if that isn't wine yet? Alright?
So one way of reading it is that yes, it becomes יין
נסך yayin nesech automatically because of what the non-Jew did, and that
applies back one stage but not two stages, that's ניצוק בר ניצוק.
nitzok bar nitzok. And the other explanation is no, it's only יין
נסך yayin nesech or סתם יינם stam yeinam if the non-Jew touches
it. And only once it hits the basket is it considered wine.
So ניצוק nitzok says if this wine is forbidden, this wine is
forbidden because that's in the category of ירד לבור. yarad labor. But
ניצוק nitzok can't make something that's not wine forbidden. Yes?
Why do you need the non-Jew touching if you have that explanation
about the בור bor being full and the wine...
No, we're dealing in the pre-before the גמרא Gemara got to the
answer of the בור bor being full. Okay? Within that explanation that
you needed the principle of ניצוק, nitzok, it says if you say
this is all wine, why do you need the principle of ניצוק?
nitzok? And the answer is is because there's wine that he touched
and wine that he didn't touch. But it's all considered to be
the same wine because it's connected through the flow.
So then when somebody takes that strainer and puts the stuff back
up here, up here, yeah, so the and it was touched already,
then what happens to the whole...
Yeah, yeah, we're still saying that. But the גמרא Gemara has two
explanations why this is a problem. Either the wine itself directly went
into the strainer, but the more interesting answer is that it didn't
and it's connected by a flow. Okay? So according to one read
is that you know, maybe you don't even need the non-Jew to
touch it or whatever. It makes one degree of flow forbidden, not
the second. But the other read says it can't make anything that's
not wine considered forbidden. It needs to be wine to be forbidden.
So actually this is already wine. And the חידוש chiddush is that
when you touch the stuff in the בור bor because it's connected
by the flow, it's like you touched the stuff in the strainer
as well. Okay? So two very interesting debates here. Debate number one
is, is this forbidden because it's been touched, or it's forbidden because
it was the energy brought it here? And then this issue of
ניצוק, nitzok, which is, is that do you learn from this two
degrees ניצוק nitzok is okay? Or do you learn from this that
really only that that no, there's no principle of two degrees ניצוק,
nitzok, maybe that is a problem, the reason this is okay is
because it's not yet wine. Okay? Back to the גמרא. Gemara. Ah,
see? It's getting fun, right? Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Okay, now, ההוא ינוקא דתנא עבודת כוכבים בשית שני. hahu
yanuka de-tana avodat kochavim be-shish shanim.
There was a young kid who learned עבודת כוכבים avodat kochavim in
six years. Now as if that wasn't impressive enough, it sounds like
it took him six years and he learned the whole מסכת, masechet,
but רש"י Rashi and רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel already say it means
not that it took him six years to learn it. He was
six years old and he had memorized and mastered the whole מסכת
עבודה זרה. Masechet Avodah Zarah. So just to make you all feel
really good, okay, here's the six year old. You know, they're like
chess geniuses right at the age of five or six, okay, so
there was a... so here you go, was the Vilna גאון, Gaon,
he had the whole thing memorized at six years old. בעו מיניה,
bo minei, they asked him, מהו לדרוך עם עובד כוכבים בגת? mahu
lidroch im oved kochavim begat? Can you go ahead and stomp grapes
with a non-Jew, which according to the משנה ראשונה mishna rishonah is
okay, okay? But apparently we're now going to be assuming משנה אחרונה.
mishna achronah. So אמר להו, amar lehu, דרכין עם עובד כוכבים בגת.
dorchin im oved kochavim begat. You are allowed to, which is basically
our משנה. mishna.
So the גמרא Gemara says, והא קמנסך בידיה? veha kemenasach beyadeih?
How could you do that? Maybe his hand will touch the wine
and that'll be considered like ניסוך, nisuch, like he'll make it יין
נסך. yayin nesech. So the obvious answer should be, what do you
mean? It's not יין yayin until it goes into the בור. bor.
But basically רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot say that we're assuming now
already משנה אחרונה. mishna achronah. I don't know how this six year
old should have should have known that or whatever. Did he really
like did he just memorize it or did like he really really
learn it? Anyway, but we're assuming now like משנה אחרונה. mishna achronah.
According to משנה אחרונה, mishna achronah, this is a problem already when
you're stomping it. It's already considered יין, yayin, okay? So the question
is how can you... what's the circumstance where you're allowed to do
it? Why isn't it that you're hiring yourself out to work איסורי
הנאה? issurei hana'ah? Because according to משנה אחרונה mishna achronah it's already
יין yayin over here, okay? So it says,
והא קמנסך בידיה? veha kemenasach beyadeih?
So the answer was דצרינן להו לידיה. ditzarinan lehu leyadeih. His hands
are tied up. And if he can't touch it with his hands,
so now it becomes an interesting question. When do you make something
יין נסך? yayin nesech? Right? I was saying is it when he
touched it, when his energy caused it to move. Here it's a
question about what if you're touching it with your feet and not
with your hands? And he seems to say if you're touching it
with your feet and not with your hands, maybe again, maybe it'll
be forbidden to be אסור באכילה assur ba-achilah or בשתייה, bishtiyah, okay,
but it won't be אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah
requires that you have that you might have touched it with your
hands, okay? And since it's not אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah you're allowed
to operate with him. You're allowed to do it with him. So
it says והא קמנסך דצרינן לידיה. veha kemenasach ditzarinan leyadeih. והא קא
מנסי ליה ברגל, veha ka mansei lei beregel, okay, but your foot
touched it. Why doesn't the foot make it forbidden? So he says,
oh, yeah, we don't even need his energy here.
We're assuming משנה אחרונה, Mishna achrona, you know, if we were assuming
משנה ראשונה Mishna rishona it wasn't wine here, the only question is
does the energy make that a problem? But if we're assuming משנה
אחרונה, Mishna achrona, then it's considered wine immediately here. So as soon
as he comes in contact with it here, forget any discussion of
energy or whatever, as soon as he comes in contact it makes
it סתם יינם. stam yeinam. So the answer is, okay, he's not,
he can't come in contact with his hands. His hands are tied
behind his back. Okay, but he's coming in contact with his feet.
Shouldn't that make it סתם יינם stam yeinam and forbidden in הנאה,
hana’ah, how can you work with him? So it says, ניסוך ברגל
לא שמיה ניסוך. nisuch beregel lo shemei nisuch. No, that doesn't count,
touching it with your feet. Now again, does it mean it doesn't
count at all and you could even drink the wine? Or a
more like reasonable middle position is, is that it doesn't make it
אסור בהנאה. asur behana’ah. If it can't really, you know, there's all
these cases where like if it can't get to the point of
being a real יין נסך, yayin nesech, like nobody is going to
do a libation of this wine to their god with their foot,
okay? So if it can't get to the point of being a
real יין נסך, yayin nesech, it won't be אסור בהנאה. asur behana’ah.
If it can't get into that עבודה זרה avoda zara realm, it
won't be אסור בהנאה. asur behana’ah. It doesn't mean it's totally okay.
I mean he's still touching it. He's just not can't touch it
with his hands. Okay? So you made sure he didn't touch it
with his hands. You tied his hands behind his back. One wonders
also like you know if you put gloves on his hands, that'll
become questions of indirect touch and so on. But touching with his
foot, maybe it's forbidden to drink, but I'm telling you what it
is not יין נסך yayin nesech at that stage. Okay? So now
it says like
this, okay, ההוא עובדא דהוי בנהרדעא. hahu uvda dehavai benaharda. Now there
was a story in
Nehardea דדשו ישראל ועובדי כוכבים להוא חמרא dedashu Yisrael ve’ovdei kochavim lahu
chamra that a non-Jew and a Jew stomped the grapes ושהיה שמואל
תלתא רגלי ushiya Shmuel telasa riglei and Shmuel held it over for
three רגלים, regalim, okay, in order to like because at every רגל,
regel, you know, there'd be a gathering of students and learning before
the
רגל, regel, and they'd drink a lot of wine at the רגל,
regel, but he waited, he didn't פסקן, pasken, okay, he wanted to
have a whole broader conversation, he wanted to crowd source the discussion,
so he wanted to wait till the רגלים regalim so he could
discuss it with a broader range of people.
מאי טעמא? mai ta’ama? Now what was the reason? What was he
trying to determine and waited till he got everybody gathered for three
different רגלים regalim to discuss? אילימא משום דקסבר, eileima mishum dekasvar,
maybe he was thinking like this, I'll have this discussion with all
the rabbis that gather for the רגל, regel, דאי משכחנא תנא דאמר
רבי נתן אסריני אפילו בהנאה. de’ei mishkachna tanna de’amar Rabbi Natan osrinei
afilu behana’ah.
Maybe I will find a תנא tanna that holds like רבי נתן
Rabbi Natan and I'll say that the wine, even though it wasn't
touched with his hands or whatever, it was only stomped, maybe it's
forbidden in הנאה. hana’ah. What רבי נתן Rabbi Natan are we talking
about? This is exactly this question, stomped but not touched etc. דתניא
מדדו. detanya medado. You are trying to measure how much wine is
in a barrel. So you know what you do? You stick your
arm in and see oh it gets up to my elbow. Or
you stick your leg in. It got up to my knee. Okay.
Very hygienic way of measuring it. בין ביד בין ברגל. bein beyad
bein beregel. ימכר אותה. yimacher otah. So the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma
says, this is actually, look, now we're getting into the real interesting
questions. What type of touch makes it forbidden? Foot, hand, direct, indirect,
does your intent matter? So the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says if
all you're doing is to do it for the sake of measuring,
that's clearly not a problem of making it יין נסך yayin nesech
and therefore again maybe you can't drink it but you can certainly
still get הנאה. hana’ah. It was only his hand was only stuck
in to measure. It's still allowed הנאה. hana’ah. That's a כוונה kavana
issue because your כוונה kavana was, the גוי's goy כוונה kavana was
clearly something else. רבי נתן אומר ביד אסור ברגל מותר. Rabbi Natan
omer beyad asur beregel mutar. Okay, with your hand it's forbidden, with
your foot it's permissible. So רבי נתן Rabbi Natan would say that
even if you just touched it, because here now the other question
is going to be the following. Does it become אסור בהנאה asur
behana’ah the moment it's touched or only if it's like moved around,
שכשוך? shichshuch? Because then it's similar to like a libation. A mere
touch is not similar. So רבי נתן Rabbi Natan says even if
it's not moved around, a mere touch, that already makes it אסור
בהנאה. asur behana’ah. Okay, so therefore maybe if we rule like that
רבי נתן Rabbi Natan there, we would rule the same by the
stomping of the grapes. That even though it was touched and it
wasn't this thing called שכשוך, shichshuch, it would make it אסור בהנאה.
asur behana’ah. Of course the גמרא Gemara says one minute, the
גמרא Gemara says אימא דאמר רבי נתן ביד ברגל מי אמר? eima
de’amar Rabbi Natan beyad beregel mi amar? But it's very clear רבי
נתן Rabbi Natan distinguishes between a hand and a leg. Okay, so
if it's just your leg and it's not a type of a
שכשוך, shichshuch, or maybe even if it is a שכשוך, shichshuch, okay,
maybe רבי נתן Rabbi Natan says that with a leg it's never
a problem, it never becomes אסור בהנאה. asur behana’ah. Alright, so therefore
the stomping, who knows, maybe even consider the stomping to be like
a שכשוך. shichshuch. But it doesn't matter, maybe רבי נתן Rabbi Natan
feels the leg is never a problem. So how do you know
that anybody would say just with the leg and in the context
of stomping it makes it אסור בהנאה? asur behana’ah? Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says אלא דאי משכחנא תנא דשרי כרבי שמעון שריא אפילו
בשתייה. ella de’ei mishkachna tanna deshari kerabbi Shimon sharyei afilu bish’tiya. No,
it's the opposite. Maybe if I find a תנא tanna that permits
like רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, שריא אפילו בשתייה. sharyei afilu bish’tiya. No,
like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. not have a way to make it
אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah even though it was only touched with the
leg, maybe I'll have a way to make it permissible even to
be drink, drink. Why? Because we'll פסקן pasken like רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. What's רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? If you look at רש"י Rashi
two lines down in the narrow lines, okay,
to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon דשרי מגע של עובד כוכבים שלא נתכוין
לנסך. deshari magash shel oveid kochavim shelo niskavein lenasech. That if that
he's very lenient and he says that if you didn't do it
with intent of נסך, nesech, of libation, it's permissible even to drink.
I mean according to him, there goes 99% of הלכות סתם יינם,
hilchos stam yeinam, right? We would only make stuff a problem if
you knew that he was intending to do a libation or maybe
if there was some reason to suspect it. But we wouldn't normally
assume it in the stomping of grapes that that was his intent,
you know, as long as it like the context makes it clear
that his intent is otherwise to stomp the grapes, it should be
okay. So what we have now is a wide range we don't
know what the answer was. But we've got a wide range of
opinions. We're back to משנה אחרונה mishnah achrona that this is a
problem, it's already יין, yayin, but the question is is it really
אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. So the first discussion with that little with
that kid was that if his hands were untied and he had
the ability to touch it with his hands then we would be
concerned he did touch it with his hands and we would assume
it becomes normally יין נסך yayin nesech סתם יינם stam yeinam and
אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah etc. And the only discussion was that his
hands were were tied together. Okay? And therefore it could be just
touching with the feet doesn't make it אסור בהנאה. assur behana'ah. In
this other case here of שמואל, Shmuel, it sounds like at least
that his hands were untied. And even though he had the ability
to touch it with his hands, we somehow are not going to
be concerned about that. So I want to point out that that's
different than the case of the kid. The case of the שמואל
Shmuel sounds like he had the ability to touch it with his
hands. And nevertheless, if he didn't, if we know he only touched
it with his feet, then that's the question of what's the story.
And he considers one extreme possibility that it's אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah
one possibility it's אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah which it rejects, it says
if it's only by the feet it's not going to be אסור
בהנאה. assur behana'ah. And the other possibility is since it lacked כוונה,
kavanah, okay, to make it יין נסך yayin nesech maybe it's even
מותר בשתייה. muttar bish'tiyah. Of course again the most logical middle stage
is to say it's only with the feet, it wasn't כוונה, kavanah,
fine, it you can drink you can't drink it but you can
still get הנאה. hana'ah. Okay, that's seems to be obviously where the
גמרא Gemara earlier seemed to settle, but the interesting question is if
it's possible he touched it with his hands but we don't know
for sure, okay, is that enough to not worry about that or
do you need a like a special scenario that his hands were
bound. All right? So now we're getting into this first big discussion
was when is it considered to be wine, now we get into
this big big discussion about what type of touch. Hands, feet, שכשוכ
shichshuch or just touch, כוונה kavanah to make it סתם יינם stam
yeinam not כוונה kavanah to make it I mean כוונה kavanah to
do ניסוך nisuch not having כוונה kavanah to do ניסוך, nisuch, okay,
all of these are wide range of factors with three possibilities: totally
מותר, muttar, totally אסור, assur, or the middle possibility you can drink
it but you can't drink it but you can get הנאה hana'ah
from it. All right? So to be continued tomorrow.